Finding Aid for Harold M. Dorr papers, 1922-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harold M. Dorr papers 1922-1973
Dorr, Harold M. (Harold McVicar), b. 1897.
851143 Aa 2; UAm
Professor of political science and dean of state-wide education at University of Michigan. Correspondence, notebooks and other papers concerning University activities, the Rotary Club, his work with the Ann Arbor Township, Washtenaw County (Mich.) Zoning Board and Planning Commission, and his work as special consultant to the occupation forces in Germany following World War II; records, 1956-1959, relating to the establishment of the Dearborn campus of the University of Michigan; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
17 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The collection was the gift of Harold M. Dorr (donor no. 1002 ) and came to the library in several accessions.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Dr. Harold M. Dorr was born in Chadwick, Mich., on Jan. 16, 1897. He received three degrees (bachelor of arts, 1923; master of arts, 1928; doctor of philosophy, 1933) from the University of Michigan.
After serving five years as high school principal and superintendent of schools in his boyhood home in Lake City, Mich., he joined the U-M faculty in 1928 becoming full professor in 1944. His specialty was American government and constitutional law.
Dorr was appointed director of the university's summer session in 1950 and, six years later, he was elevated to the newly created post of dean of statewide education. In that capacity he was responsible for the Extension Service, the Audio-Visual Center and other off-campus educational functions. Dorr played an important role in the organization of the U-M-Flint and in the development of the U-M-Dearborn.
In 1949 Dorr was a special consultant commissioned to study legislatures and legislative procedures in the American Zone in Germany. In 1950 he was assigned to Germany as a governmental specialist by the US State Department.
Dorr was a member of the American Political Science Association, the Conference of Midwest Political Scientists (president, 1949-50), the American Academy of Political and Social Science, the American Society for Public Administration of University Professors (a member of the National Council, 1941-54), Pi Sigma Alpha and Phi Kappa Phi.
At the state level, his service included consulting work with the Department of Public Instruction and as a member of the Michigan Civil Service oral examining boards. He also was active in adult education and taught extension classes and lectured extensively throughout the state. Dorr was equally active in civic and local affairs. He served on the Washtenaw County Selective Service Board for more than 20 years and on the Ann Arbor Township Zoning Board and Planning Commission. He was president of the Ann Arbor Rotary Club (1952-53) and district governor (1954-55).
Harold M. Dorr died on January 31, 1973.
The Harold M. Dorr collection provides excellent documentation of the professor's activities both in and out of the classroom. There is extensive material detailing his long-time activities with the Ann Arbor Rotary and as a member of the zoning board and planning commission of Ann Arbor Township. Also documented is his role with the U-M Extension Service and his interest in the university's state-wide education program. The series in the collection are: Family; Correspondence; Other materials; Notebooks; Manuscripts of writings; Department of Political Science; Ann Arbor Township activities; and Topical and organizational activities. Portions of the collection are unprocessed.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.: Township); Ann Arbor Rotary Club.; City planning--Michigan.; Dorr, Harold M. (Harold McVicar), b. 1897.; Germany.; Rotary International.; University of Michigan. Dean of State-Wide Education.; University of Michigan--Dearborn.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Chimes (University of Michigan); Rickover, Hyman George.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Rotary International.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Family
  - "The Dorr Odyssey" (family genealogy and history) (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - By date
    - 1951-1955, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - By activity
    - Rotary Club 1956-1957, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Candidates for dean of the Dearborn Campus of the University of Michigan 1956-1958, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Rotary Club 1959-1966, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Other materials
  - University of Michigan activities
    - 1922-1949, 25 folders (Box 2)
  - Rotary Club
    - 1950-1954, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Various
    - 1964-1966 undated, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets 1949-1954 (Box 3)
- Notebooks
  - Minutes of University of Michigan Council 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan records 1942-1945 (Box 3)
  - Academic calendar 1945 (Box 3)
  - Ann Arbor Rotary Club (history of) 1947 (Box 3)
  - Rotary International Assembly 1954 (Box 3)
- Manuscripts of writings
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Department of Political Science
  - Various activities (Box 5)
- Ann Arbor Township activities
  - Ann Arbor Township Zoning Board; and Ann Arbor Township Planning Commission (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor Township Zoning Board; and Ann Arbor Township Planning Commission (Box 7)
    (continued)
  - Ann Arbor Township Zoning Board; and Ann Arbor Township Planning Commission (Box 8)
  - Ann Arbor Township Zoning Board; and Ann Arbor Township Planning Commission (Box 9)
- Topical and organizational activities
  (unprocessed)
  - Flint (Box 10)
  - Wolverine Girls State (Box 10)
  - Selective Service (Box 10)
  - Washtenaw County Community College (Box 10)
  - Speaking engagements (Box 11)
  - Conferences and seminars (Box 11)
  - Chamber of Commerce (Box 11)
  - Correspondence files (Box 12)
  - German exchange (Box 12)
  - Midwest Political Science Conference (Box 12)
  - Republican Party activities (Box 12)
  - American Association of University Professors (Box 13)
  - German visit (Box 13)
  - State-wide education (Box 13)
  - Miscellanea (Box 13)
  - Rotary Club papers 1954-1969 (Box 14)
  - Flint College materials (Box 14)
  - Committee on Hatcher Inauguration (Box 14)
  - University activities (Box 14)
  - Newspaper clippings, obituaries and citations (Box 14)
  - Montross controversy 1944-1948 (Box 14)
  - Extension Service files re continuing education, adult education, institutes and conferences (Box 16)
  - Dearborn campus 1956-1959 (Box 17)
  - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 17)
    The Photographs file includes 1922 photo of the staff of Chimes, a University of Michigan student publication; group photographs of the faculty of the University of Michigan Department of Political Science; photographs relating to Dorr's activities with Rotary International; and miscellaneous group photographs, including Dorr with George Romney and Hyman Rickover (see also oversize UAm).